So I want to take you on a trip
سوف أأخذكم في رحلة
to an alien world.
الى عالم الكائنات الغريبة
And it's not a trip
انها لست رحلة
that requires light-years of travel,
تتطلب مئات السنوات الضوئية من السفر
but it's to a place
انه مكان
where it's defined by light.
كل شيء فيه محدد بالضوء
So it's a little-appreciated fact
ان هناك معلومة لا يعيها الكثير
that most of the animals in our ocean
ان معظم الكائنات التي تقطن محيطنا
make light.
تولد الضوء
I've spent most of my career
لقد قضيت كل مسيرتي المهنية
studying this phenomenon called bioluminescence.
ادرس الظاهرة الحيوية التي تدعى الضوء الحيوي
I study it because I think understanding it
لقد درستها لاني اظن ان فهم هذه الظاهرة
is critical to understanding life in the ocean
هو بحد ذاته فهم للمحيط باكمله
where most bioluminescence occurs.
المكان الذي تحدث فيه ظاهرة الضوء الحيوي
I also use it as a tool
وقد استخدمته - الضوء - كوسيلة
for visualizing and tracking pollution.
من اجل تعقب وتحديد مواقع التلوث
But mostly I'm entranced by it.
ولكن في الحقيقة انا مذهولة به
Since my my first dive in a deep-diving submersible,
منذ اول غوص عمق قمت به بغواصة
when I went down and turned out the lights
عندما ذهبت الى الاعماق ورايت هذه الاضواء
and saw the fireworks displays,
والتي تشبه الالعاب النارية
I've been a bioluminescence junky.
لقد اصبحت مهووسة الضوء الحيوي
But I would come back from those dives
وسوف احاول اليوم ان انقل لكم هذا الهوس بالضوء الحيوي
and try to share the experience with words,
بواسطة الكلمات
and they were totally inadequate to the task.
والتي هي في معظم الحالات عاجزة عن ذلك
I needed some way to share the experience directly.
خطر في بالي طريقة اخرى لكي اشارككم ما لدي مباشرة
And the first time I figured out that way
واول ما خطر على بالي
was in this little single-person submersible
هو هذه الغواصة الصغيرة التي تتسع لشخص واحد فسحب
called Deep Rover.
والتي تدعى " مستكشفة الاعماق "
This next video clip,
في ملف الفيديو التالي
you're going to see how we stimulated the bioluminescence.
شوف نريكم كيفية تحفيز الضوء الحيوي
And the first thing you're going to see
واول شيء يمكن ان ترونه
is a transect screen
هو شاشة شفافة
that is about a meter across.
بعرض متر واحد
(Video) Narrator: In front of the sub,
(ملف فيديو ) المتحدث : في مقدمة الغواصة
a mess screen will come into contact
هناك شاشة عملاقة سوف تخولك
with the soft-bodied creatures of the deep sea.
للتواصل مع مخلوقات المحيط في الاعماق السحيقة
With the sub's lights switched off,
وعندما تطفىء اضواء الغواصة
it is possible to see their bioluminescence --
يمكنك حينها من ان تشاهد الضوء الحيوي الصادر عنها
the light produced when they collide with the mesh.
ان هذه الاضواء تتولد عند الاصطدام بالشباك
This is the first time
هذه المرة الاولى
it has ever been recorded.
التي يتم فيها تسجيل هذا
Edith Widder: So I recorded that with an intensified video camera
إيديث ويدير : لقد صورت هذا الفلم بواسطة كاميرا
that has about the sensitivity
لها حساسية مثل حساسية
of the fully dark-adapted human eye.
العين البشرية في المناطق المظلمة
Which means that really is what you would see
وهذا يعني ان هذا ما سوف ترونه
if you took a dive in a submersible.
ان قمتم بالغوص بواسطة غواصتنا
But just to try to prove that fact to you,
وسوف احاول ان ابرهن لكم هذه الحقيقة
I've brought along some bioluminescent plankton
لقد احضرت معي بلانكتونات الضوء الحيوي
in what is undoubtedly a foolhardy attempt
انها محاولة مثيرة مستحيلة لا محالة
at a live demonstration.
من اجل استعراض حي للضوء الحيوي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, if we could have the lights down
هلا اطفأتم الاضواء من فضلكم
and have it as dark in here as possible,
لكي يعم الظلام قدر الامكان
I have a flask
لدي هنا " عبوة "
that has bioluminescent plankton in it.
فيها بلانكتونات الضوء الحيوي
And you'll note there's no light coming from them right now,
وان لم يظهر الضوء الان ..
either because they're dead --
ربما لان بلانكتونات الضوء الحيوي قد ماتت
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
or because I need to stir them up in some way
او ربما لانه يجب ان يجب ان احركها قليلاً
for you to see what bioluminescence really looks like.
لكي ترون كيف يبدو الضوء الحيوي حقاً
(Gasps)
(تعجب)
Oops. Sorry.
آه .. عذراً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I spend most of my time working in the dark; I'm used to that.
لقد قضيت كل عمري اعمل في الظلام .. لذا انا معتادة على ذلك
Okay.
حسناً
So that light
ان هذا الضوء
was made by a bioluminescent dinoflagellate,
الضوء الحيوي يظهر من خلال ذات السياط
a single-celled alga.
انها طحالب وحيدة الخلية
So why would a single-celled alga
ولكن لماذا تحتاج طحالب وحيدة الخلية
need to be able to produce light?
لاصدار الضوء ؟
Well, it uses it to defend itself from its predators.
انها في الحقيقة تستخدمه لابعاد المفترسين
The flash is like a scream for help.
ان هذا الضوء مثل طلب مساعدة
It's what's known as a bioluminescent burglar alarm,
انه ما يمكن ان ندعوه الضوء الحيوي للاغاثة
and just like the alarm on your car or your house,
انه مثل الانذار الموجود في منزلك او سيارتك
it's meant to cast unwanted attention onto the intruder,
انه يعني انه يعمل حينما يدخل معتد او يخترق احدا مكانا لا يجب ان يكون فيه
thereby either leading to his capture
والضوء يهدف اما للاشارة الى المعتدي
or scaring him away.
او من اجل اخافته
There's a lot of animals that use this trick,
وهناك الكثير من الكائنات التي تستخدم هذه الحيلة
for example this black dragonfish.
على سبيل المثال سمكة التنين هذه
It's got a light organ under its eye.
لديه منتجات ضوء اسفل عينيه
It's got a chin barbel.
وعلى ذقنه
It's got a lot of other light organs you can't see, but you'll see in here in a minute.
بل لديه الكثير من منتجات الضوء التي لايمكنكم رؤيتها الان .. ولكن سيمكنكم ذلك خلال دقيقة
So we had to chase this in the submersible for quite sometime,
كان علينا ان نلاحقه بواسطة الغواصة لفترة من الزمن
because the top speed of this fish is one knot,
لان سرعة هذه السمكة القصوى هي عقدة واحدة
which was the top speed of the submersible.
وكذلك سرعة الغواصة
But it was worth it,
ولكن الامر كان يستحق الجهد المبذول
because we caught it in a special capture device,
لقد استطعنا ان نلتقط .. بسبب جهاز استشعار خاص
brought it up into the lab on the ship,
موضوع في مخبر على السفينة
and then everything on this fish lights up.
وماهي الا هنيهة حتى اضيئت السمكة باكملها
It's unbelievable.
انه مشهد لا يصدق
The light organs under the eyes are flashing.
ان منتجات الضوء تضيء
That chin barbel is flashing.
والجسد باكمله مضاء
It's got light organs on its belly that are flashing,
ولديه ايضا منتجات ضوء على بطنه
fin lights.
وعلى زعانفه
It's a scream for help; it's meant to attract attention.
انها نداء استغاثة .. تهدف الى طلب العون
It's phenomenal.
انها ظاهرة مميزة
And you normally don't get to see this
وعادة لا ترون هذا
because we've exhausted the luminescence when we bring them up in nets.
لان الشبكات تكون قد استنفذت خلايا الضياء الحيوي
There's other ways you can defend yourself with light.
وهناك طرق اخرى يمكنك بواسطتها حماية نفسك بواسطة الضوء
For example, this shrimp
على سبيل المثال هذا الجمبري
releases its bioluminescent chemicals into the water
انه يطلق حزمة من الضوء الحيوي الكيمائي في المياه
just the way a squid or an octopus would release an ink cloud.
كما يطلق الحبار او الاخطبوط سحابة حبر
This blinds or distracts the predator.
لكي يعني او يشتت المفترس
This little squid is called the fire shooter
ان هذا الكائن هنا .. يدعى القاذف
because of its ability to do this.
لانه يملك القدرة على القيام بذلك
Now it may look like a tasty morsel,
ربما يبدو مثل لقمة لذيذة
or a pig's head with wings --
او كرأس خنزير عائمة بأجنحة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but if it's attacked,
ولكن ان هاجمه احد
it puts out a barrage of light --
فانه يطلق حزمة من الضوء
in fact, a barrage of photon torpedoes.
في الحقيقة انها " طوربيدات " ضوئية
I just barely got the lights out in time
بالكاد استطعت ان التقط هذا الضوء
for you to be able to see those gobs of light
سوف ترون هذه الومضات من الضوء
hitting the transect screen
التي ترتطم بالشاشة الحساسة
and then just glowing.
ومن ثم تشع
It's phenomenal.
انه مشهد مثير
So there's a lot of animals in the open ocean --
هناك الكثير من الحيوانات في المحيط
most of them that make light.
والعديد منها يمكنه انتاج الضوء
And we have a pretty good idea, for most of them, why.
ونعرف الكثير عن سبب انتاج الاضواء
They use it for finding food, for attracting mates,
انهم تستخدمه من اجل ايجاد الطعام .. واستدراج الازواج
for defending against predators.
وحماية انفسهم من المفترسين
But when you get down to the bottom of the ocean,
وعندما تغوص الى عمق المحيط
that's where things get really strange.
يمكن ان ترى الكثير من العجائب
And some of these animals
وبعض هذه الحيوانات ربما هي الملهم
are probably inspiration for the things you saw in "Avatar,"
الاساسي في شخصيات فلم " آفاتار "
but you don't have to travel to Pandora to see them.
ولايتوجب عليك ان تذهب الى كوكب ناندورا لكي تراهم
They're things like this.
انهم هنا .. انهم يبدون هكذا
This is a golden coral, a bush.
ان هذه الاعشاب الذهبية
It grows very slowly.
تنمو ببطىء شديد
In fact, it's thought that some of these
في الحقيقة بعض هذه الاعشاب
are as much as 3,000 years old,
تبلغ من العمر 3000 عاماً
which is one reason that bottom trawling should not be allowed.
وهي احد اهم الاسباب الذي يجب ان يمنع لاجله " الاجتثاث من القاع " - سحب الرمال لاجل وضعها على اليابسة -
The other reason is this amazing bush glows.
والسبب الاخر هو ان هذه الاعشاب تلمع
So if you brush up against it,
ان حركتها او استثرتها
any place you brushed against it,
فان في المكان الذي تم استثارته
you get this twinkling blue-green light
فانها تصدر اضواء زرقاء-خضراء
that's just breathtaking.
وهي اضواء مبهرة جداً
And you see things like this.
وكما ترون هناك اشياء كهذه
This looks like something out of a Dr. Seuss book --
انها تبدو كاحدة شخصيات كتب " الدكتور سوس "
just all manner of creatures all over this thing.
وهي كائنات في كل المحيط
And these are flytrap anemones.
وهي عبارة عن افخخ هوائية
Now if you poke it, it pulls in its tentacles.
وان وخزتها فانها تغلق على نفسها
But if you keep poking it,
وان استمريت بذلك
it starts to produce light.
فانها تنتج الضوء الحيوي
And it actually ends up looking like a galaxy.
حتى تبدو كما المجرة
It produces these strings of light,
انها تنتج حزماً من الضوء
presumably as some form of defense.
كنوع من انواع الدفاع عن النفس
There are starfish that can make light.
و نجمة البحر هذه تنتج الضوء ايضاً
And there are brittle stars that produce bands of light
هناك انواع من نجوم البحر تنتج طيفاً من الاضواء
that dance along their arms.
والتي تتراقص على ايديها
This looks like a plant,
هذه تبدو مثل النبتة
but it's actually an animal.
ولكنه في الحقيقة حيوان بحري
And it anchors itself in the sand
وهي توثق نفسها في ارض المحيط
by blowing up a balloon on the end of its stock.
عن طريق نفخ بالون هواء في مؤخرة جسدها
So it can actually hold itself in very strong currents,
ويمكنها ان توثق نفسها ضد تيارات مياه قوية
as you see here.
كما ترون هنا
But if we collect it very gently, and we bring it up into the lab
وان استطعت ان تحملها بهدوء واعادتها الى المخبر
and just squeeze it at the base of the stock,
والضغط بصورة خفيفة على قاعدتها
it produces this light
فانها تنتج الضوء الحيوي
that propagates from stem to the plume,
الذي يخرج من القاع الى الاطراف
changing color as it goes,
ويتغير على طول المسير
from green to blue.
من الاخضر الى الازرق
Colorization and sound effects
حتماً المؤثرات الصوتية والضوئية
added for you viewing pleasure.
تمت اضافتها من اجل متعتكم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But we have no idea why it does that.
ولكننا لا نملك اي فكرة لماذا تقوم بهذا
Here's another one. This is also a sea pen.
وهذه واحدة اخرى .. انه " قلم البحر "
It's got a brittle star hitching a ride.
انه يملك ايدي على شكل نجمة البحر
It's a green saber of light.
وهو ينتج ضوءا اخضر
And like the one you just saw,
مثل هذا الذي ظهر الآن
it can produce these as bands of light.
ويمكن ان يتنج حزماً من الضوء
So if I squeeze the base,
ان قمت بعصره من القاعدة
the bands go from base to tip.
فان الحزم الضوئية تنطلق الى الاطراف
If I squeeze the tip, they go from tip to base.
وان قمت بعصره من الاطراف فان الحزم الضوئية تنطلق الى القاعدة
So what do you think happens if you squeeze it in the middle?
وماذا تظنون انه يمكن ان يحدث ان قمتم بعصره من المنتصف
(Gasps)
(ضحك)
I'd be very interested in your theories about what that's about.
سوف اكون مهتمة بسماع نظرياتكم في هذا الخصوص
So there's a language of light in the deep ocean,
هناك لغة ضوئية تحدث في اعماق المحيط
and we're just beginning to understand it,
وقد بدأنا في استيعابها
and one way we're going about that
وواحدة من الطرق التي سنقوم بها من اجل ذلك
is we're imitating a lot of these displays.
هو تقليد تلك اللغة بواسطة هذه الاجهزة
This is an optical lure that I've used.
هذا الجهاز البصري
We call it the electronic jellyfish.
ندعوه " قنديل البحر الالكتروني "
It's just 16 blue LEDs
انه يملك 16 ضوءا ازرق
that we can program to do different types of displays.
ويمكن ان نبرمجمه لكي يضيء كما نريد
And we view it with a camera system I developed called Eye-in-the-Sea
ويتم استعراض الاضواء بواسطة نظام طورناه يدعى " عين في البحر "
that uses far red light that's invisible to most animals,
وهو يستخدم ضوءا احمر بعيد المدى من اجل الحيوانات الخفية
so it's unobtrusive.
ولايمكن تميزه بسهولة
So I just want to show you
وانا اريد ان اريكم بعض
some of the responses we've elicited
الاستجابات التي التقطناها
from animals in the deep sea.
من قبل بعض الحيوانات في اعماق المحيطات
So the camera's black and white.
ان كميرة التصوير .. تصور بالابيض والاسود
It's not high-resolution.
انها ليست عالية الدقة
And what you're seeing here is a bait box
ولكن ما سوف ترونه هنا .. هو صندوق
with a bunch of -- like the cockroaches of the ocean --
ويحيط به الكثير من صراصير البحر
there are isopods all over it.
والتي هي منتشرة في كل مكان
And right in the front
في الامام يوجد
is the electronic jellyfish.
قنديل البحر الالكتروني
And when it starts flashing,
وعندما يبدأ بالوميض
it's just going to be one of the LEDs that's flashing very fast.
اي عندما تبدأ احدى اضواءه بالوميض بسرعة
But as soon as it starts to flash --
بعد قليل سوف يبدأ الجهاز بالوميض
and it's going to look big, because it blooms on the camera --
وسوف يكون الضوء كبيراً .. لانه يرتطم بعدسة الكميرا بكم كبير
I want you to look right here.
ولكن اريدكم ان تنظروا هنا
There's something small there that responds.
هناك شيء صغير هنا سوف يتجاوب
We're talking to something.
نحن نتحدث الى شيء ما على ما يبدو
It looks like a little of string pearls basically --
ان الضوء سيبدو كما لو انه عقد من اللؤلؤ
in fact, three strings of pearls.
في الحقيقة سوف ترون 3 عقود - استجابة -
And this was very consistent.
وكان هذا امرٌ واقعي جداً
This was in the Bahamas at about 2,000 feet.
لقد حدث في اعماق الباهامس على عمق 2000 قدم
We basically have a chat room going on here,
لدينا في الحقيقة غرفة محادثة هنا
because once it gets started, everybody's talking.
وما ان يبدأ الوميض
And I think this is actually a shrimp
حتى ترى كل شيء يتجاوب حتى الجمبري
that's releasing its bioluminescent chemicals into the water.
الذي يصدر الضوء الحيوي الكيميائي في المياه
But the cool thing is, we're talking to it.
وهو امرٌ رائع .. نحن نتحدث اليهم
We don't know what we're saying.
ولا ندري ما نقوله لهم
Personally, I think it's something sexy.
بصورة شخصية اعتقد ان هذا الامر مثير
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then finally,
واخيراً
I want to show you some responses that we recorded
اريد ان اريكم بعض الاستجابات التي قمنا بتسجيلها
with the world's first deep-sea webcam,
بواسطة كميرة الفيديو الرقمية الاولى في الاعماق
which we had installed in Monterey Canyon last year.
انه شيء قمنا برتكيبه في خندق مونيري السنة الماضية
We've only just begun to analyze all of this data.
ونحن نعمل اليوم على تحليل تلك المعلومات
This is going to be a glowing source first,
وتلك الكميرا هي مصدر غني بالمعلومات
which is like bioluminescent bacteria.
خاصة فيما يتعلق بالبكتريا التي تصدر الضوء الحيوي
And it is an optical cue
انها عبارة عن دليل بصري
that there's carrion on the bottom of the ocean.
لما يحدث هناك في ذلك الخندق
So this scavenger comes in,
جاء نابش القمامة اول الامر
which is a giant sixgill shark.
وهو قرش كبير الحجم
And I can't claim for sure
وانا لا استطيع ان ادعي على وجه التاكيد
that the optical source brought it in, because there's bait right there.
ان المصدر الضوئي جذبه .. لانه كان هناك الكثير من المغريات في تلك المنطقة
But if it had been following the odor plume,
ولكن ان كان يحاول اللحاق بالكائن المدعو عمود الحبر
it would have come in from the other direction.
لكان قد جاء من الطرف الاخر
And it does actually seem to be trying
والفكرة انه كان يحاول ان
to eat the electronic jellyfish.
ياكل قنديل البحر الالكتروني
That's a 12-foot-long giant sixgill shark.
هذا هو القرش الكبير طوله 12 قدم
Okay, so this next one is from the webcam,
حسنا المشهد التالي ايضاً من كميرة تصوير رقمية
and it's going to be this pinwheel display.
ولكن هذه المرة الضوء يشبه
And this is a burglar alarm.
ضوء الانذار في حال الخطأ
And that was a Humboldt squid,
وقد جذب هذا الضوء حبار هومبولت
a juvenile Humboldt squid, about three feet long.
انه حبار هومبولت صغير طوله حوالي 3 اقدام
This is at 3,000 feet in Monterey Canyon.
وهو يعيش في عمق 3000 قدم في خندق مونتيري
But if it's a burglar alarm, you wouldn't expect it to attack the jellyfish directly.
ولانه ضوء على شاكلة الانذار .. فلم نكن نتوقع ان يهاجم قنديل البحر الالكتروني
It's supposed to be attacking what's attacking the jellyfish.
ربما كان يتوجب ذلك
But we did see a bunch of responses like this.
ولكنه لم يرى اضواء من هذا القبيل
This guy is a little more contemplative.
لذا هو حذر قليلاً
"Hey, wait a minute.
انظروا قليلاً ..
There's supposed to be something else there."
انه يحاول ان يكتشف الامر
He's thinking about it.
انه يفكر حياله
But he's persistent.
انه متوجس
He keeps coming back.
ولكنه مصر ويعود ويحوم حول الضوء
And then he goes away for a few seconds
وها هو يبتعد قليلاً
to think about it some more,
ومن ثم يقترب مرة اخرة
and thinks,
ويقول في نفسه
"Maybe if I come in from a different angle."
ربما علي ان اقترب من زاوية اخرى
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Nope.
لا لا ..
So we are starting to get a handle on this,
لقد بدأنا بتجربة مثيرة هنا
but only just the beginnings.
ونحن مازلنا في بداية الطريق
We need more eyes on the process.
ونحتاج المثير لكي نعي تلك الآلية
So if any of you ever get a chance to take a dive in a submersible,
اذا اردتم ان تسنح لكم الفرصة من اجل الغوص في تلك الغواصة
by all means, climb in and take the plunge.
فعليكم السعي من اجل ذلك
This is something that should be on everybody's bucket list,
انه امرٌ يجب على الجميع القيام به
because we live on an ocean planet.
لاننا نعيش على كوكب
More than 90 percent, 99 percent,
90 % .. بل 99%
of the living space on our planet
من مخلوقاته الحية
is ocean.
تعيش في المحيطات
It's a magical place
انه عالم سحري
filled with breathtaking light shows
مليئ بالانواء الرائعة وعروض الضوء
and bizarre and wondrous creatures,
والمخلوقات المميزة
alien life forms
التي تشبه كائنات الفضاء
that you don't have to travel to another planet to see.
والتي لا تتطلب منكم السفر الى خارج الكوكب من اجل مشاهدتها
But if you do take the plunge,
كل ماعليكم هو القيام بعملية غوص
please remember to turn out the lights.
ولكن تذكروا .. من فضلكم .. ان تطفؤا الانوار
But I warn you,
ولكني أحذركم
it's addictive.
انه امرٌ سوف تدمنون عليه
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)